Finding Aid for Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (University of Michigan) records, 1937-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (University of Michigan) records 1937-1996, 1960-1995
University of Michigan. Senate. Advisory Committee on University Affairs.
12.5 linear feet
87311 Bimu B31 2
The Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) serves as the executive body of the University of Michigan Senate. SACUA represents the faculty as a whole in its work on University policy and its power to nominate faculty to governance committees. The records consist of documents generated by SACUA and its committees. The bulk of the material originates from SACUA's committees and includes work on academic affairs, affirmative action, faculty grievance procedures, research, student quality, and tenure.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records are transferred in periodic accessions by the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (Donor # 5029 and # 8656 ).
The Senate Advisory Committee for University Affairs records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The SACUA record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 11-12
Since its creation in 1937, the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) has played a major role in faculty governance. In his report "Faculty Governance at the University of Michigan," historian Nicholas Steneck defines faculty governance as "the means by which the Regents and their designated representatives provide some self government to, seek advice from, and ask for consent from the faculty." In the 19th century, faculty governance was the responsibility of the University Senate, a body made up of the entire faculty. By the early 20th century, the university had outgrown this system of governance: the increased number of faculty made the Senate unmanageably large, and did not reflect the growing importance of professional administrators. These inadequacies led to a series of reorganizations of faculty governance. In 1906, the powers of the Senate were transferred to a smaller executive body called the Senate Council. In 1931, the Senate Council was replaced with another body called the University Council, which included both faculty and professional administrators.
By 1937, the University Council proved to be too large, and SACUA was created to represent the Senate in the University Council and to report to the Senate. At this stage, SACUA consisted of some members elected by the Senate and others chosen by the Dean's Conference. In 1940, the importance of SACUA was diminished with the creation of another executive governing body, the Advisory Board on University Policies. The new body was appointed by the Board of Regents, and therefore weakened faculty control over university governance. By 1948, the University Council had ceded most of its functions to these smaller executive bodies, and was dissolved. That same year, SACUA was restructured to serve as the executive body of the Senate, with members elected at large by the Senate. In 1965, the University Senate again reorganized faculty governance by creating a body called the Senate Assembly. The new body consisted of sixty-five members elected to represent the various colleges and schools of the university. The Assembly served as the legislative arm of the Senate and elected the members of SACUA. Presently, SACUA continues to serve as an executive arm of the Senate Assembly. It consists of nine members elected for three year terms. In addition to their duties as executives of the Senate, the members of SACUA are responsible for nominating faculty members to various governance committees.
The Senate Advisory Council on University Affairs Records consist of correspondence, minutes, and reports relating primarily to the economic status of the faculty and the administration of the University. The records measure 12.5 linear feet and range from 1937-1996, the bulk of which spans 1960-1995. The records are arranged in four series: Minutes; Core Records; Boards, Committees and Commissions and Photographs.
Subjects:
Teacher participation in administration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Committee on the Economic Status of the Faculty.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Senate. Advisory Committee on University Affairs.; University of Michigan--Students--Discipline.
- Minutes 1937-1995
  The Minutes series, 1937-1995 (1.25 linear feet) consists of minutes from SACUA meetings from 1937 to 1995, mostly in binders. The minutes include brief reports from SACUA committees, and cover a wide range of subjects, such as faculty pay and benefits, educational policy, campus planning, and student relations.
  - 1937-1943, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1944-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1982 (Box 1)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1988 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (Box 1)
  - 1989 (Box 1)
    (includes Senate Assembly minutes)
  - 1992 (Box 2)
  - 1993 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - 1993-1994 (Partial minutes and scattered) (Box 2)
  - 1994-1995 (Bound) (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
- Core Records 1950-1998
  The Core Records series contains material generated by SACUA itself, as opposed to its committees or subcommittees. The core records series includes correspondence, chairman's papers, documents on tenure and grievance cases, and SACUA reports on a variety of subjects. The series also contains a folder of material explaining the structure of SACUA and the Senate Assembly, which might help researchers to understand the structure of faculty governance.
  - Chairmen
    - 1950, Russell Dodge (Box 2)
    - 1951, Thomas Francis, Jr. (Box 2)
    - 1952, Carl Fischer (Box 2)
    - 1954, Algo Henderson (Box 2)
    - 1955/56, Allen Smith (Box 2)
    - 1956/57, John C. Kohl (Box 2)
    - 1957/58, John C. Kohl (Box 2)
    - 1994/95, Jean Loup
      - Correspondence 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Perspectives article with George Brewer 1995 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1954-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1963 (Box 3)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (unbound) (Box 3)
    - 1974-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 4)
      (includes inter-SACUA e-mail)
  - Reports
    - General 1937-1950, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Intra-Committee Reports 1940-1948 (Box 4)
  - Grievance Cases
    - 1982-1983 (Box 11)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 11)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
  - Tenure Cases
    - Paul Cuncannon 1942-1943, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Hans Pick 1943 (Box 4)
    - C.N. Wenger and Carl Dahlstrom 1942-1944, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Tenure case 1982-1983
      - Folder1 (Box 4)
      - Folder 2 (Box 11)
    - Tenure Case 1994 (Box 11)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2024 ]
    - Tenure Case 1995 (Box 11)
  - Discontinuance of Academic Programs 1977-1985, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - University Television Development 1968 (Box 5)
  - SACUA-Senate Assembly Material 1984-1994 (Box 5)
    (reports explaining the structure and procedures of faculty governance)
  - Grievance and Tenure cases
    - Case Files 1984-1998, 53 folders (Box 12)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
- Boards, Committees and Commissions 1957-1995
  The Boards, Committees and Commissions series, 1957-1995 (6.5 linear feet) represent the records of the various organizations that report through SACUA to the Senate. Interesting records include the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, the Committee on the Economic Status of the Faculty (CESF), and the Committee for a Multicultural University. CESF reports are particularly valuable because of their annual reports discussing faculty compensation. The Bylaws/Rules Committee subseries, 1959-1997 (.25 linear feet) consists of bound correspondence and reports surrounding the formation of policy for the senate and the university, including rules governing the makeup of the senate's governing bodies and the demographics of the university faculty. The Bylaws Committee changes its name to the Rules Committee in December 1977. The Grievance Subcommittee subseries, 1983-1996 (.75 linear feet) contains correspondence, reports, and research information pertaining to the university grievance policy. This material was part of an accession from Professor Thomas E. Moore, who served on SACUA, the Grievance Subcommittee, and was president of the University of Michigan chapter of the American Association of University Professors (AAUP).
  - Committee Overviews 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics
    - Minutes and Reports 1959-1966 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1960-1965 (Box 5)
    - General Records 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Committees and Subcommittees
    - Academic Affairs Committee
      (known as Educational Policies Committee until 1968)
      - 1958-1968 (Box 5)
      - 1965 (Box 5)
      - 1968-1971 (Box 5)
      - 1977-1982 (Box 5)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 5)
    - Academic Freedom Lecture 1990-1995 (Box 6)
    - Affirmative Action Program Advisory Council 1977-1987 (Box 6)
    - Alumni Association Study Committee 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Task Force on the Appeal of Tenure Decisions 1994 (Box 6)
    - Subcommittee on Appointments and Procedures circa 1954-1955 (Box 6)
    - Budget Study Committee 1993-1995 (Box 6)
    - Committee on Business Affairs 1964-1967 (Box 6)
    - Subcommittee on Campus Planning and Development 1963-1965 (Box 6)
    - Committee on the Economic Status of the Faculty (CESF)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 6)
      - 1944-1945 (Box 6)
      - 1944-1946 (Box 6)
      - 1944-1946 Related Correspondence (Box 6)
      - 1953 (Box 6)
      - 1948-1960 (Box 6)
      - 1960-1966 (Box 6)
      - 1966-1989, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - 1990 (Box 7)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - Civil Liberties Board
      - 1973-1975 (Box 7)
      - 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    - Special Subcommittee on Disclosure 1968 (Box 7)
    - Distinguished Faculty Governance Award 1995 (Box 7)
    - Task Force on the Evaluation of Administrators/Deans 1992-1995 (Box 7)
    - Faculty Affairs Committee 1993 (Box 7)
    - Subcommittee on the Faculty Center 1966 (Box 7)
    - Faculty Club Planning 1960-1967 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Faculty Government at University of Michigan-Flint 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Faculty Hearing Committee 1984-1994 (Box 7)
    - Advisory Board on Faculty Perspectives 1994 (Box 7)
    - Financial Affairs Advisory Committee
      - 1969-1977 (Box 7)
      - 1977-1983 (Box 7)
      - 1992-1994 (Box 8)
    - Flexible Benefits Advisory Committee 1994 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Governance 1994 (Box 8)
    - Government Relations Committee 1993-1994 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Grievances 1983-1995 (Box 8)
    - Health Affairs Advisory Committee 1994-1995 (Box 8)
      (continues Medical Affairs Committee)
    - Faculty Advisory Council on Higher Education 1967 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Improvement of Instruction
      - 1960 Report on Evaluation of Instruction (Box 8)
      - 1961-1963 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Lecture Series 1973 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Major Medical Insurance 1958-1965 (Box 8)
    - Medical Affairs Advisory Committee 1992-1994 (Box 8)
      (continued as Health Affairs Committee)
    - Miscellaneous Sub-Committee Material
      - 1953-1959 (Box 8)
        (includes "Tenure," "Severance Pay," and "Responsibility of Faculty to Society")
      - Life on the Other Side of the Tenure Track: Non-Tenure-Track Instructional Staff at the University of Michigan, 1993 (Box 8)
    - Committee for a Multicultural University 1992-1995 (Box 8)
    - Nominating Committee
      - 1957-1960 (Box 8)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 8)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 8)
    - Outside Employment 1944 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Political Activity; correspondence 1973 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on the Professoriate 1993-1994 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Public Relations 1965 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Research Policy 1965 (Box 8)
    - Research Policies Committee 1992-1994 (Box 8)
    - Senate Rules Committee 1993-1995 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Staff Excellence 1960-1968 (Box 8)
    - Subcommittee on Student Quality circa 1963 (Box 8)
    - State Relations Committee (Box 9)
      (known as "The Proper Role of the University of Michigan in the Educational System of the State")
      - 1961-1969 (Box 9)
      - 1969-1972 (Box 9)
      - 1974-1987 (Box 9)
    - Student Relations Committee
      - 1959-1967 (Box 9)
      - 1965 (Box 9)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 9)
      - 1969 (COOP Material) (Box 9)
      - 1969-1978 (Box 10)
      - 1979-1987 (Box 10)
      - 1992-1995 (Box 10)
    - Tenure Committee 1992-1995 (Box 10)
    - Conference on the University 1961-1963 (Box 10)
    - Advisory Committee on University Budgets (ACUB) 1994 (Box 10)
    - Subcommittee on University Freedom and Responsibility 1960-1965 (Box 10)
    - Faculty Research Program on University Governance 1973-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - University Hospital 1944 (Box 10)
    - University Relations Committee 1993-1994 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Year-Round Integrated Operations 1961-1963 (Box 10)
    - Salary Policy Under Year-Round Operation 1964-1965 (Box 10)
  - Bylaws/Rules Committee
    - 1959-1968 (Box 13)
    - 1968-1975 (Box 13)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 13)
  - Grievance Subcommittee
    - Resignations/Dismissals 1995 (Box 13)
    - New Grievance Report 1995 (Box 13)
    - UM Records Policy and Confidentiality 1995 (Box 13)
    - SACUA Survey-Peer Grievance Procedures 1993 (Box 13)
    - Grievance Procedures 1983-1995 (Box 13)
    - American with Disabilities Act-Medical Information Confidentiality 1993 (Box 13)
    - UM Grievance Summary 1983-1993 (Box 13)
    - Cognate Panel-Grievance Review Boards (GRB) 1995 (Box 13)
    - FOIA 1994 (Box 13)
    - David Adamany (Wayne State University) Statement 1988 (Box 13)
    - David Moerman Senate Assembly Report 1989 (Box 13)
    - SACUA Recommended Grievance Procedures Changes 1993 (Box 13)
    - Faculty Ombuds Data 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - Student Ombuds Data 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - American Association of University Professors (AAUP) 1996-1997 (Box 13)
    - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), Grievance Data 1983-1994 (Box 13)
    - Consultation and Conciliation Services, UM (Box 13)
    - Faculty Legal Defense, Indemnification 1992-1994 (Box 13)
    - University of Minnesota Grievance Policy 1994 (Box 13)
    - Employment Coordinator Grievance Procedures Recommendations 1989 (Box 13)
    - Michigan State University Grievances 1993-1996 (Box 13)
    - University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) Grievance Procedures, Privilege and Tenure Document 1991-1995 (Box 13)
    - Pastors' Alliance 1994-1995 (Box 13)
    - Livermore/Nordby Grievance Report 1983 (Box 13)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of unidentified group photographs of SACUA members ca. 1994-1995.
  - SACUA group photographs circa 1994 (Box 10)